<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Great bastard, protector of the little one done out of French ; and for which a proclamation, with a reward of 5000 lewedores, to discover the author, was published.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41872</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1663A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R41767</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">31360598</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 31360598</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110746</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41872)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110746)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1739:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Great bastard, protector of the little one done out of French ; and for which a proclamation, with a reward of 5000 lewedores, to discover the author, was published.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 5-31.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Re-printed at Cologne :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Wing gives London as place of publication.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Louis --  XIV, --  King of France, 1638-1715.</term>
               <term>James, --  Prince of Wales, 1688-1766.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  1660-1714.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Louis XIV, 1643-1715.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110746:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110746:1"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Great Baſtard,</hi> PROTECTOR OF THE <hi>Little One.</hi> Done out of <hi>French.</hi> And for which a <hi>Proclamation,</hi> with a Reward of 5000 Lewe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dores, to diſcover the Author, was Publiſhed.</p>
            <p>Re-printed at <hi>Cologne,</hi> 1691.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:110746:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110746:2"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Great Baſtard,</hi> Protector of the Little One, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:110746:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:110746:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:110746:4"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:110746:4"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Great Baſtard,</hi> Protector of the Little One, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WE find in <hi>Holy Writ,</hi> that, in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Law, it was expreſly provided by the ſupreme Legiſlator, <hi>That a Baſtard ſhould not enter into the Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Lord, even to the tenth Generation:</hi> But it ſeems the unhappy Kingdom of <hi>Franc</hi> allows the Baſtard himſelf, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to enter into the Congregation, but to ſettle himſelf upon the Throne, and to bear it higher than all the preceeding Kings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:110746:5"/> him, with had a better Right to do it, as being the Off-ſpring of Kings, and not <hi>the Sons of the People,</hi> the proper Term the <hi>Roman</hi> Law gives to <hi>Baſtards.</hi> We have heard of the <hi>Salick Law,</hi> in force in that Kingdome, for a great many Ages, by which the Crown of <hi>France cannot fall from the Sword to the Diſtaff;</hi> but ill the bleſſed Days of our <hi>Auguſt Monarch,</hi> we never had the Happineſs to be acquainted with a Law or Cuſtom, by which that was in the Power of a Queen of <hi>France,</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide us an Heir to the Crown, without the Concurrence of her Husband, and to impoſe upon us for our King, a Brat of another Man's making All the Reign of our <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible Monarch,</hi> has been a conſtant Series of Wonders; but among them all, this is none of the leaſt, That he who was, in the Opinion of all the World, <hi>the Son of a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Gentleman,</hi> from his Birth till the end of <hi>the Prince of</hi> Conde<hi>'s Wars,</hi> has had the good Fortune to be ever ſince no leſs <hi>than the Son of</hi> Lewis <hi>the Thirteenth.</hi> After this, let no Body call in queſtion the commonly ſuppoſed Fable of the Tranſmutation of <hi>Iphis</hi> from a Woman to a Man, ſince to be tranſlated from a <hi>Baſtard</hi> to a <hi>Son lawfully begotten,</hi> is equally as difficult.</p>
            <p>Among a great many other Quarrels, I have with the <hi>Engliſh Nation,</hi> this is one,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:110746:5"/> That they are a People too nice in belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Miracles; and their Haughtineſs is ſuch, as they ſcorn, forſooth, to believe Impoſſibilities; for albeit, they, and all the reſt of the World about them, are firmly perſwaded, that <hi>the little Bable Prince of Wales</hi> was never of Queen <hi>Marys</hi> bearing, much leſs of King <hi>James</hi>'s begetting; yet if theſe Infidels had been as <hi>well mannerly credulous</hi> as we in <hi>France</hi> have been, of the wonderful Tranſmutation of our <hi>Lowis le Grand,</hi> they needed not have made all this Noiſe about <hi>the little Impoſtor-Infant,</hi> but might have comforted themſelves in the hopes, that he, who was a Spurious Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> to Day, might ſome Years hence, by a new <hi>French</hi> way of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> become a lawfully begotten King of <hi>England.</hi> But the Miſchief of all, is, theſe ſtiff-necked Hereticks, ever ſince they fell off from the Communion of the Holy Church, make bold to call in queſtion all our Miracles; and ſuch a one as this would be, I am af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid they would ſtick at, among others.</p>
            <p>Good God! how happy had it been for <hi>France,</hi> yea, for a great part of the World, that the <hi>French</hi> had been as great Infidels, upon th point of Miracles, as the Heretick <hi>Engliſh!</hi> and that our <hi>Lowis the Fourteenth</hi> had been hurl'd out of <hi>France</hi> when but <hi>Dauphin of Viennois,</hi> as <hi>the little mock Prince
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110746:6"/> of Wales</hi> has been out of <hi>England.</hi> when ſcarce well handled into the Light! What diſmal Tragedies has our <hi>French Impoſtor</hi> caus'd in <hi>Chriſtendom!</hi> how many Cities laid in Aſhes, Countries ruin'd, Families extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, and millions of Lives ſacrific'd to the Vanity and Ambition of a <hi>Baſtard!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Hugonots</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> of all People in the World, have moſt reaſon to be aſhamed of their Conduct, with Relation to <hi>this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grate Monſter,</hi> in the time of his Minority, and of <hi>the Prince of</hi> Conde's <hi>Wars:</hi> And theſe People, who diſown a thouſand things in the Catholick Religion, meerly upon the account of their being, in their Opinion, <hi>irreconcilable to Reaſon,</hi> did ſtrangely contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict, not only <hi>common Fame,</hi> but even <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it ſelf,</hi> in being brought to think, that it was poſſible, that <hi>Lowis the Fourteenth</hi> ſhould be the true Son of <hi>Lowis the Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth,</hi> after near half a <hi>Jubilee</hi> of Years paſt in Marriage betwixt him and <hi>Ann</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> his Queen, without the leaſt hope of Iſſue, with all the concurring Signs of a natural Impotency upon his ſide. But theſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men have paid dear enough for their Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and have had ſufficient time and occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to read their paſt Folly, in their preſent Affliction, and to call to mind, with Regret, their unaccountable Madneſs in aſſiſting him to re-aſcend the Throne of <hi>France,</hi> whom
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:110746:6"/> almoſt <hi>the whole Nation, the Princes of the Blood,</hi> and the <hi>Parliament of Paris,</hi> had combin'd together, to tumble down, and had cetainly done it, if the <hi>Hugonots</hi> had not turn'd the Scale. Theſe poor <hi>Hugonots</hi> have had ſo many ſad Occaſions ſince to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent their Fault, that I confeſs it's ſcarce <hi>generous</hi> to upbraid <hi>the Miſerable</hi> with the Follies they cannot now amend, and which had brought upon them ſo many Misfortunes. And yet I muſt beg leave to tell them. That as their Zeal to <hi>Lewis the Fourteenth</hi>'s unjuſt Intereſt, was the original Cauſe, in my Opinion, of Heaven's thus afflicting them by his Hands; ſo it was indeed the true Motive that induc'd this <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngrate</hi> to ruin them. For thus it was, that he and <hi>his Jeſuitick Cabal</hi> reaſon'd among themſelves; If the <hi>Hugonots,</hi> in the late Prince of <hi>Conde</hi>'s Wars, when the Crown was <hi>at Stake,</hi> were able to turn the Ballance, and to draw Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory and Succeſs to the ſide they eſpouſed, which at that time was <hi>ours:</hi> By the ſame Parity of Reaſon, If the ſame <hi>Hugonots</hi> ſhall at any time hereafter be induc'd to join a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, and to take our Enemies; part, they will without all doubt turn the Scale on the other ſide, and prove as dangerous Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies as formerly they were Friends; and thence, by a Diabolical way of Reaſoning, it was concluded, that it was the true Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:110746:7"/> of the Crown, that the <hi>Hugonots</hi> ſhould be utterly deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>By the way, I muſt tho' contrary to my Inclination, do a piece of Juſtice to <hi>Lowis the Fourteenth,</hi> in vindicating him from a common Aſperſion caſt upon him by the <hi>Hugonots,</hi> and it's this: Over and above the fouleſt Ingratitude imaginable, (in which Charge I heartily agree with them) he is chargeable with a to them, they will needs load him to the boor, with no leſs than <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury and Breach of Faith,</hi> in not obſerving the famous Edict of <hi>Nants,</hi> which was granted to them by King <hi>Henry the Fourth,</hi> and declared by him to be in all time co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, an irrevocable and fundamental Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the State; which Edict, ſay they, <hi>Lewis the Fourteenth</hi> ſwore at his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation inviolably to obſerve. I confeſs this is a heavy charge; but to ſpeak no worſe of the Devil than he deſerves, in my Opinion our <hi>Lewis le Grand</hi> is not chargea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble upon that Scove, as not being bound to tho Obſervance of that Edict, even tho' ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſworn it: If we ſhall conſider, that by the expreſs words of the Edict it ſelf, King <hi>Henry</hi> obliges <hi>himſelf and his lawful Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors only,</hi> that is, thoſe who ſhall ſucceed to the Crow of <hi>France</hi> in a lawful Deſcent of Royal Blood. Now, I think no Man will ſay, That by this Clauſe of the Edict, an
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:110746:7"/> extraneous Perſon, ſuch as <hi>our Interloper Lewis the Fourteenth is,</hi> can be included; and therefore, as having none of the Royal Blood of <hi>France</hi> in his Veins, he cannot be juſtly charg'd with Perjury or Breach of Faith, in not obſerving one Edict, which was declared and meant to oblige only the lawful Succeſſors of King <hi>Henry the Fourth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here I cannot but relate a Diſcourſe I had once with one of <hi>the Fathers of the Capucian Order;</hi> the very day after the Revocation of the Edict of <hi>Nants,</hi> and which may ſerve to anſwer one Objection naturally ariſing from what I have ſaid upon this Head. All <hi>Paris</hi> was filled with the Noiſe of his Affair, and in every corner, both <hi>Papiſt</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant</hi> was reaſoning upon it; among the reſt, the good <hi>Capucin</hi> and I would needs turn both <hi>States-men</hi> and <hi>Caſuiſts</hi> on the Subject. We loſt, betwixt us, all the Arguments we could fall upon, to vindicate, if poſſible, the King's ſo apparently unjuſt Action; and in the end we came to reaſon how far the King was obliged to the Obſervance of the Edict of <hi>Nants,</hi> upon the account of his not being indeed the lawful Succeſſor of <hi>Henry the Fourth,</hi> the Granter of it. <hi>But,</hi> ſaid I, <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, tho' I ſhould agree, that the King is not obliged by that Edict at firſt, for the Reaſon we have named, yet his Poſterior Swearing to obſerve it, makes him as lyable to the Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:110746:8"/> of it, as if he were really the true Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor of</hi> Henry the Fourth, <hi>and of the Royal Blood of</hi> France. To this the <hi>Capucin</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned me a very ſatis factory Anſwer: <hi>Sir,</hi> ſays he, <hi>it ſeems you are but little acquainted with the Caſuiſtick Doctrine and Principles of the Jeſuits, and have not the Happineſs to be acquainted with Father</hi> le Cheſe, <hi>the King's Confeſſor, ſo well as I; and therefore I'll tell you one Evaſion, a Wit, like his, will ſoon find out to remove all needleſs Scruples from the King's Mind, ariſing, from his Swearing the Edict of</hi> Nants, <hi>and it's this: The words of the Oath, which the King did take at his Coronation, was theſe; And ſeeing this Edict was declared by King</hi> Henry the Fourth, <hi>our Grand-father of glorious Memory, to be irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocable, and that his lawful Succeſſors, the ſucceeding Kings of</hi> France, <hi>ſhould ſwear the ſame at their Coronation, therefore we do hereby promiſe and ſwear faithfully and invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lably to obſerve the ſaid Edict all the days of our Life-time. Now, theſe being the very words of the King's Oath,</hi> (continues the <hi>Capucin</hi>) <hi>how proper and eaſy was it for the Revered Father</hi> le Cheſe <hi>to tell him, Sir, you are not at all obliged by this Oath, becauſe it leans upon, and contains in its very Boſom a Suppoſition, upon the removal of which, the whole Oath it ſelf does neceſſarily fall,</hi> viz. <hi>Your Majeſty's being the Grand-child of</hi> Henry the Fourth, <hi>which neither you your ſelf, nor
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:110746:8"/> no Body elſe does believe: So that if your Majeſty has ſworn an Oath, wherein there is an expreſs Suppoſition that you are the Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>child of</hi> Henry the Fourth, <hi>which you are not, the Oath it ſelf, as leaning on that falſe Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, muſt neceſſarily fall with it, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes in it ſelf void. I hope you are wiſer,</hi> (concludes the <hi>Capucin</hi> to me) <hi>but to think that Father</hi> le Cheſe <hi>might uſe all this Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom with his ignorant bigotted Pupil, enſlaved to his Direction, eſpecially that he is acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with all the Villanies of his Life, and in particular with his criminal Privacies with the Dauphineſs.</hi> Thus far the <hi>Capucin</hi>'s Diſcourſe and mine, and I muſt ſay, upon Reflection, I cannot devine an Evaſion which Father <hi>le Cheſe</hi> could have fallen upon more plauſible, to perſwade his enſlav'd Pupil to revoke the <hi>Edict of Nants,</hi> than this the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pucin</hi> hinted at.</p>
            <p>But I know the Reader will tell me, What means all this puther upon a meer Suppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that <hi>Lowis le Grand</hi> is a <hi>Baſtard,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out making it appear, or proving that he is ſo? I acknowledge, that of all the Tasks one ever ventured upon, that of proving a Man to be a <hi>Baſtard</hi> is the hardeſt; for when a Woman deſigns to bring another than her Husband to her Bed, ſhe uſes not to order ſuch and ſuch Perſons to ſtand by, that they may bear Teſtimony of her Crime:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:110746:9"/> And tho' ſome Women may come the length of Inadvertence or Impudence, in being too open in their Amours, yet when they have to do with a <hi>Gallant</hi> that's concern'd in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and oblig'd by his <hi>Character</hi> to be more reſerved in his Pleaſures, it's not be be imagined but ſhe will be taught to play her part, if not <hi>chaſtly,</hi> yet <hi>cautiouſly.</hi> All the World knows, that the <hi>Cardinals</hi> of <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelew</hi> and <hi>Mazarin</hi> were capable of keeping their own Secrets; and yet it's to be regrat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that their <hi>Amours</hi> with <hi>our invincible Monarch's Mother</hi> were hard enough to be concealed, ſo many are the Spies about the Courts of Princes.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Ann</hi> of <hi>Auſtria</hi> found a way to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide an Heir to <hi>Lowis the Thirteenth,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out putting him to the Pains of getting it himſelf, will appear clearly enough, if we take a view of all the Circumſtance that meet in this Affair, which all taken together, leaves us no room to doubt of that <hi>Queens</hi> Concern for <hi>perpetuating</hi> her <hi>Husband's Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory</hi> at <hi>any Coſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Common Fame</hi> was ever lookt upon as a great Preſumption of the Truth of a thing, eſpecially if joined to other <hi>concurring Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances:</hi> and never did that <hi>prating God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſs</hi> extend her Voice louder, than in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming to the World the Spurious Birth of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:110746:9"/> our <hi>Auguſt Monarch.</hi> Time was when ſhe did not whiſper it in Corners, but expreſs'd it in publick <hi>Pictures, Plays, Farces,</hi> and what not? Modeſty will not allow me to mention the baudy Shapes of thoſe two ſorts of Bread, called to this day, <hi>the Queens Bread,</hi> and <hi>the Cardinal's Bread,</hi> ſold thro' <hi>Paris,</hi> and in moſt Places of <hi>France;</hi> ſo that at that time one could ſcarce ſit down to eat, but he was put in mind of the <hi>Queens and the Cardinal's Amours.</hi> It were in vain to enumerate the thouſand part of the <hi>Satyrs</hi> and <hi>Raſquils</hi> on this Subject, for a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Years; each Pen out-vying one another, in the Glory of propagating to Poſterity the Love-Paſſions of theſe <hi>two mighty Cardinal Miniſters of State;</hi> let this one upon <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal Richelew,</hi> affixt on his <hi>Palace,</hi> ſerve for all:
<q>
                  <l>What means th' ungrate <hi>French</hi> to hate</l>
                  <l>The only true Support of State?</l>
                  <l>What greater Favour could there be</l>
                  <l>Show to the King, Queen, State, all three,</l>
                  <l>That to provide, by his unwearied Care,</l>
                  <l>The King a Son, the Queen a Husband, and the State an Heir?</l>
               </q> Impotency is not of thoſe Imperfections a Man is moſt unwilling to take with, being that which un-mans him, and renders him the Scorn of <hi>his own,</hi> and the Abhorrence of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:110746:10"/> the <hi>other Sex:</hi> It can only be proved by <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions;</hi> and theſe are for the moſt part reducible, either to <hi>his Indifference for the fair Sex in general,</hi> or for <hi>his own Wife in particular; the Weakneſs of his Conſtitution,</hi> or <hi>his co-habiting with a Woman of a ſound Body and proportion'd Age for a conſiderable time, without having any Iſſue by her.</hi> All theſe Preſumptions, and ſome more than perhaps <hi>Decency</hi> will allow me to name, will be found in <hi>Lowis the Thirteenth,</hi> the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Father of our <hi>Auguſt Monarch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I think there can be no greater Proof of a Man's <hi>Indifference for the fair Sex</hi> in general, or his own Wife in particular, than when a Man, in the Heat of his Youth, has a Right, by Marriage, to the Bed of a beautiful and young Princeſs, has her conſtantly in his View, and in his Power, and yet at the ſame time can, for ſome Years together, abſtain from thoſe Embraces which Marriage has not only made <hi>lawful,</hi> but a <hi>Duty:</hi> And this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wonted Coldneſs in Youth is the more to be jealouſed, that, previous to the Marriage, the Man did expreſs an <hi>eager Impatience</hi> to enjoy his <hi>young Bride;</hi> for the ſubſequent Coldneſs and Abſtinence does clearly inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate a Conſciouſneſs of his being miſtaken of himſelf, and that upon Tryal he has found his Power not anſwerable to his Will.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:110746:10"/>
            <p>Of all this, we have a pretty clear Inſtance in <hi>Lowis the Thirteenth:</hi> Upon his being Married by Proxy to <hi>Anna</hi> of <hi>Auſtria, Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> afterwards <hi>Mother to our invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible Monarch,</hi> he expreſs'd the greateſt Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerneſs to enjoy her, and having gone the length of <hi>Burdeaux</hi> to meet her, his Deſires vented themſelves in the following <hi>Letter,</hi> ſent her ſome few days before her Arrival:
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Madam,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>SInce I cannot, according to my longing De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, find my ſelf near you at your Entry into my Kingdom, to put you in Poſſeſſion of the Power I have, and of that entire Affection I have in my Breaſt to love and ſerve you; I ſend you <hi>Luyenes,</hi> one of the moſt truſtieſt of my Servants, to Salute you in my Name, and to tell you, that you are expected by me with the greateſt Impatience, to offer unto you <hi>MY SELF:</hi> I pray therefore receive him favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably, and believe what he ſhall tell you, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> from your moſt dear Friend and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>LOWIS.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText> The <hi>Strain</hi> of this <hi>Letter</hi> ſeems to be <hi>warm enough,</hi> and the word <hi>Offer of himſelf,</hi> is pretty expreſſive, as coming from a young <hi>Bridegroom</hi> to a young and beautiful <hi>Bride.</hi> Now, who would have dream'd but this <hi>Skirmiſhing</hi> by Letters ſhould have produced
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:110746:11"/> a <hi>fix'd Battel</hi> at meeting? But, alas! our Youngſter having Bedded his Queen but for the ſpace of two hours, riſes up from his Nuptial-bed, too late conſcious to himſelf of his Unfitneſs for <hi>the Sports of Venus:</hi> And albeit he was in his Queens Company every day for four Years thereafter, his falſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires never led him once again, during all that time, to try a <hi>ſecond Rencounter:</hi> Yea, it was expected by every Body he ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have ventured to Bed the Queen again, if <hi>his Favourite Luyenes</hi> had not trickt him into it the very Night of his <hi>Siſters</hi> Marriage with <hi>the Prince of Piedmont;</hi> for <hi>Luyenes</hi> finding the King in a good jolly Humor, and talking more wantonly than ordinary, he graſps him out of his Bed in his Arms, and throwing a Night-Gown about him, brings him unexpectedly into the Queens Bed. It was indeed pretended, that the Reaſon of this four Years Abſtinence was for fear the Marriage-bed might hinder <hi>the King's Growth,</hi> and <hi>enervate his Strength;</hi> And yet it's hard to believe, that ſuch a <hi>politick Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration</hi> could prevail with a Man that had any <hi>boiling Blood</hi> in his Veins; but every Body will be apt, at the firſt daſh, to draw this Conſequence from it, that there was more in it of <hi>a Winter-Chilneſs</hi> than uſually ſuits with Youth.</p>
            <p>From the beginning of the Year 1619; to 1638, <hi>King Lowis the Thirteenth</hi> continued to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:110746:11"/> Cohabit with his Queen, and often in his <hi>Melancholy Fits,</hi> to which he was naturally ſubject, he would complain to his <hi>Confidents,</hi> That he knew certainly the Queen would have no Children to him. Upon which fell out a <hi>remarkable Paſſage,</hi> that ſerves mightily to unriddle ſome difficulties in this Affair; one day at <hi>Fountainbleau,</hi> the time of his Brother <hi>Monſieur's</hi> Wars againſt him, being in a ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len Fit, he began to regrate to ſome few a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him, his Misfortune of not having Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of his own Body, which he ſaid was the cauſe of <hi>Monſieur's</hi> Inſolence againſt him, and of <hi>his Power with the People,</hi> as being <hi>preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Heir</hi> of the Crown. Hereupon ſome of them began to tell him, That for Reaſons of State, it was very fit to procure a Divorce from the Queen, and that perhaps another Wife might bring him Children to Heir the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> and put <hi>Monſieur</hi> beſide the <hi>Cuſhion.</hi> But <hi>Luyenes,</hi> who knew the Kings Infirmity beſt, taking him aſide, told him with his uſual freedom, <hi>Sire, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs you reſolve to ruine your ſelf for good and all, let there never be the leaſt mention made in time coming of a Divorce from the Queen, for if any ſuch thing ſhall come to her Ears, ſhe will be ſure to lay the blame of her Barrenneſs upon your Majeſty, and this every Body will believe, and which will render Monſieur's Pretenſions inſupportable.</hi> And indeed it was from this Conſideration, that the motion of a Divorce
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:110746:12"/> was ever afterwards laid aſide, leaſt the Queen ſhould be provoked to tell out the Truth, and thereby <hi>Monſieur's</hi> Intereſt ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated a pin higher than ſuited with the Kings ſafety.</p>
            <p>There is another great preſumption of ones <hi>Impotency,</hi> when a Man evinces himſelf to be indifferent, not only for his own Wife, but for <hi>the whole fair Sex</hi> in general, <hi>Lowis the Thirteenth</hi> gave ample proofs of <hi>this ſort of Vertue,</hi> if it be one, having been never ſeen to caſt one ſingle warm glance at any of the Beauties of the Court and never heard to utter one Expreſſion that could be interpret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Amorous.</p>
            <p>Of this indifference of his for the fair Sex, there is one pretty inſtance, in an Expreſſion he had to <hi>Monſieur</hi> his Brother, upon the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of his Marrying <hi>the Duke of Lorrain's Daughter,</hi> againſt the King's Will; <hi>Monſieur</hi> having told him, by way of excuſe, that he chus'd rather to Marry at any rate, then to Live in Whoredom, and one of the two he ſaid his Conſtitution obliged him to. <hi>Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> replies the King, <hi>You and I it ſeems are of different tempers, for I could Live all my Life without either of them.</hi> Here was a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, tho' untimous confeſſion of his <hi>Indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference,</hi> if not <hi>Impotency,</hi> and indeed <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur</hi> was not wanting to improve it in his <hi>Circular Letters,</hi> he wrote to his <hi>Partiſans,</hi> a few Months after, upon his retiring to <hi>Bruſſels.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:110746:12"/>
            <p>There is another <hi>Story</hi> much of the ſame nature, that paſſed betwixt the King and his Favorite <hi>Luyenes,</hi> about the Divorce from the Queen, when it was firſt talkt of: <hi>Luyenes</hi> told him, That the only way to ſtop the Queens Mouth in the matter of the <hi>Divorce,</hi> was for the King to give an evidence, that her Barrenneſs was not from his fault, by trying to get Children by ſome other Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; and hereupon he mention'd one of the Handſomeſt Ladies about Court, as a fit Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs for him. The King anſwered coldly, <hi>Mais je vous aſſure Luyenes, je ne ſonge pas a telles choſes: But I aſſure you,</hi> ſays he, Luye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, <hi>I do not think upon theſe things.</hi> And ſo the Diſcourſe was dropt.</p>
            <p>I ſhall only name one other inſtance more of the King's <hi>indifference for the fair Sex,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was ſo publick, and had ſo much of Raillery in it: The King being one day play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at Cards with <hi>Mademoſelle Ramboulet,</hi> it happen'd that the King alledged upon her, ſhe had dropt a Card on deſign, ſaying, he would have it, be where it will; the Lady finding ſhe was diſcover'd, ſlipt the Card in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her Breaſt, ſaying, <hi>Sir, I am aſſured you will not take it out here:</hi> Which was true, for the King gave over any further ſearch, when he ſee the Card was in her Boſom.</p>
            <p>A great many attributed this <hi>indifference</hi> of the King's for his own Lady, and all other Women, to <hi>the weakneſs of his Conſtitution,</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:110746:13"/> and indeed he was of the tendereſt and ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt imaginable, being from his Birth weak in his Limbs, and <hi>Aſthmatick</hi> to his Dying day. The <hi>Duke of Eſpernon</hi> rallying one day with the King's Phyſician, told him, he was afraid the King might over heat himſelf in the Embraces of a Young and Beautiful Queen. The Phyſician nodding his Head, anſwer'd him, <hi>It muſt be a great heat that will thaw his Majeſty's Ice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But tho' <hi>Lowis the Thirteenth</hi> had been a <hi>juſt Admirer of his own Queen, and of the fair Sex in general,</hi> and had neither been branded with <hi>Impotency,</hi> nor known to be of a <hi>weakly Conſtitution,</hi> what a wonderful thing was it, that what a Man could not do in <hi>the heat of his Youth,</hi> he ſhould in the beginning of <hi>the Autumn of his Age,</hi> and that there ſhould be <hi>Twenty Three Years</hi> betwixt their Marriage and the Birth of their firſt Child? I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the <hi>Poets</hi> tell us, that <hi>Jupiter,</hi> when he was to beget <hi>Hercules,</hi> was neceſſitated to make a <hi>Night three times longer than the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary,</hi> ſo difficult was it even for <hi>the Father of the Gods</hi> to beget <hi>an Hero,</hi> but our <hi>Invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible Hero, Lowis le Grand,</hi> required a long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er time to be gotten than <hi>Hercules,</hi> and <hi>Twenty Three Years</hi> was little enough time to produce our <hi>Auguſt Monarch.</hi> What a ſhame was it for <hi>Cardinal Richelew</hi> to throw away ſo much pains to no purpoſe? And how eaſie had it been to have made the King
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:110746:13"/> a Father, and the Queen a Mother, in the twentieth part of that time, if he had but underſtood <hi>the new Engliſh way</hi> of getting and bearing Children? But it ſeems the Art of impoſing <hi>Infant Princes</hi> was not then brought to that perfection it has been of late, and <hi>Anna of Auſtria</hi> was not ſo good a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient in the Trade as <hi>Mary of Modena.</hi> What needed the former have made herſelf the talk of all <hi>France,</hi> for her <hi>Intrigues</hi> with her <hi>two Cardinals?</hi> It had been the eaſieſt thing in the World to make her a Mother, without the trouble of one <hi>ſingle throw:</hi> a cloſe <hi>Baliſter about the Bed,</hi> and a <hi>convenient Paſſage at the head of it,</hi> with a <hi>wary Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife,</hi> and one or two more <hi>truſty Confidents,</hi> might have done juſt as well.</p>
            <p>But the Curſe of all was, our <hi>Lowis the Thirteenth</hi> was neither to be impos'd upon in ſuch an Affair, nor could be brought into <hi>the Deſign</hi> himſelf; his Malice to his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the next Heir, tho' at War with him, came not up to that length, as to cheat him of the Throne: And tho' <hi>Lowis the Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth</hi> had been capable of ſo great a <hi>Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> or rather <hi>Madneſs,</hi> his Brother <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur</hi> was too much concern'd to let the Queen impoſe upon him, one to exclude him from the Crown: During the Queens bigneſs, <hi>Monſieur</hi> had his conſtant Spies about her, to watch her Motions, and to tell him eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing that paſt: Upon the News of the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:110746:14"/> Queens being <hi>in Labour, Monſieur</hi> was not out of the way, but haſtens away to her <hi>Bed-Chamber,</hi> and his Sedulity and Watchfulneſs was ſcarce allowable in Modeſty, the leaſt Circumſtance about the <hi>Mother</hi> and <hi>Child</hi> did not eſcape his <hi>prying Curioſity,</hi> and <hi>the Field of Nature it ſelf</hi> was laid open to his view; ſuch is the Misfortune of Princeſſes, when bearing Children, in prejudice of other Mens Rights. <hi>Monſieur</hi> retiring himſelf to his Chamber, in a Melancholy Mood, (as he had good reaſon) was asked of by <hi>Eſpernon,</hi> what he had ſeen: <hi>Alas!</hi> ſays he, <hi>I am ſure I ſaw it come out, but who the Devil put it in, I know not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queen <hi>Mary of Modena</hi> took a ſhorter cut, and a more modeſt Method of Lying in; ſhe would neither allow <hi>the Princeſſes</hi> concerned to ſearch into her <hi>Bigneſs,</hi> nor permit any in their Name to be preſent at <hi>her Labour;</hi> the poor <hi>Princeſs of Denmark</hi> was hurried away to the <hi>Bath,</hi> upon the pretence of her Health, and <hi>the Queen Dowager</hi> was not brought in till <hi>the Game was over;</hi> and who can blame a <hi>Modeſt Italian</hi> to be more reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in <hi>the Secrets of Nature</hi> than a <hi>blunt Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard?</hi> How happy was it for <hi>the firſt,</hi> that inſtead of <hi>two Princeſſes</hi> at a diſtance, ſhe did not meet with a <hi>Bluſtering Duke of Orle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,</hi> to peep more narrowly into the Scheme of her Contrivances, and render her and her Plot ridiculous.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:110746:14"/>
            <p>But to return to the Happy Birth of our <hi>Lowis le Grand,</hi> it ſeems all the Endeavours of <hi>Cardinal Richelew,</hi> to provide an <hi>Heir</hi> for <hi>France,</hi> were unſucceſsful, whether <hi>hss Brain</hi> and his <hi>other parts</hi> were not of a piece, or his preſſing Cares of State, join'd to ſome natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Impediment, were the cauſe of it, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell; but it was reſerved for a Perſon of <hi>a meaner Condition,</hi> tho' of a more <hi>robuſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution,</hi> to effectuate, what this <hi>Conſummate Church Man</hi> had attempted in vain; <hi>Monſieur le Grand,</hi> a Gentleman of a comely Perſon, and ſprightly Spirit, and a courtly Genius, was lookt upon as the fitteſt Perſon to make up the defects of <hi>an Impotent King,</hi> and a <hi>Wearied Favorite-Cardinal.</hi> This <hi>Carpet Knight</hi> was admitted into the <hi>Embraces</hi> of the Queen, and by her <hi>teeming Belly,</hi> ſhe found, within a few Months, that ſhe had hit upon a fit <hi>Stallion</hi> to propagte the Royal Family of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's generally thought this Gentleman was not ſo much the Queens own choice, as that of <hi>Richelew,</hi> and that this <hi>Refin'd Miniſter</hi> perſuaded the Queen to entertain <hi>Monſieur le Grand</hi> for her Gallant, out of a meer Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of State, as being more likely to make the Queen a Mother, than he himſelf was; and this is the rather believed, that it is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally known, that immediately after the Queen was found to be with Child, <hi>M. le Grand</hi> was diſmiſt the Court, upon the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:110746:15"/> pretence of being made <hi>Lieutenant Criminal of Provence,</hi> the wily <hi>Cardinal</hi> fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his intimacy with the Queen might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice him in her Favour; and indeed after <hi>this Jobb</hi> was done, the <hi>Cardinal</hi> had no more uſe for him, as the ſequel made it too evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pliny</hi> tells us a Story of the <hi>Wolf,</hi> That he never ſees his <hi>Sire,</hi> becauſe, ſays he, he is Murdered by the reſt of the Wolves, out of envy, that he was prefer'd by the ſhe Wolf before them. The ſame Fate had the Father of this <hi>Rapacious Creature, Lowis the Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth,</hi> for being noos'd into the Conſpiracy of <hi>Monſieur de Monmorancy,</hi> he was behead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at <hi>Tholouſe,</hi> by the <hi>Cardinal's</hi> expreſs Command, who was unwilling the Queen ſhould have an abler <hi>Gallant</hi> than himſelf for the future.</p>
            <p>I cannot but regrate the Fate of this poor Gentleman, in being firſt brought to the Bed of a Queen, and thereafter in having his Head chopt off, meerly that he might not tell <hi>Tales,</hi> or give any <hi>Jealouſy</hi> to his <hi>Rival</hi> in the Queens Favour; yet I judge him Happy in this, that he did not Live to ſee the <hi>Monſter</hi> he had begotten.</p>
            <p>There happen'd a memorable paſſage at his Death, which was this. Being all along, after his Condemnation, laid aſleep, with an aſſurance of a Pardon, even upon the Scaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, to the end he might not diſcover any of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:110746:15"/> his <hi>Criminal Secrecies</hi> with the Queen; at laſt, being deſir'd <hi>to lay down his Head,</hi> for the blow, he came to underſtand, too late, that he was cheated out of his Life, and juſt when he was beginning to expreſs himſelf in theſe Words: <hi>O! la Vanite d'eſtre aime d'une fame cruele,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>O! the Vanity of being Lov'd by a Woman cruel, and devoted to the Villanous Counſels of a Church Man.</hi> Here the Fatal Ax did put an end to the Sentence, and to his Life together.</p>
            <p>This end had <hi>Monſieur le Grand,</hi> Father of our <hi>Auguſt Monarch;</hi> and it's but juſt his Son ſhould bear the Name of <hi>Le Grand,</hi> not as an <hi>Epithet,</hi> but as the <hi>Sirname of his Father, Le Grand,</hi> by way of Epithet, being never his due; and thus was <hi>Cardinal Richelew</hi> ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged upon him, for being a fitter and abler <hi>Gallant</hi> to the Queen than himſelf, tho' at firſt he was not only <hi>the Privado,</hi> but the <hi>firſt Incourager</hi> of their <hi>Amours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When I am on this Subject, I cannot but mention <hi>a Droll ſert of Letter,</hi> Written about that time by <hi>Monſieur</hi> to the <hi>Duke of Lorrain,</hi> his Brother in Law, from <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> which was afterwards found among <hi>the Duke of Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain's</hi> Papers taken at St. <hi>Michel,</hi> which was to this purpoſe. <hi>Your Highneſs accuſes me unjuſtly, for not obtaining from</hi> Monſieur le Grand, <hi>when he was with me, a Declaration of his Privacies with the Queen, which you ſay would have mightily furthered my Affairs:
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:110746:16"/> But, Sir, tho'</hi> M. le Grand, <hi>at ſome certain times, out of a tranſport of fury againſt the Queen, for her <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nkindneſs, as he term'd it, would confeſs to me the whole Secrets paſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Queen and him, yet the very next moment he would paſs from all he had ſaid, and affirm, that what he ſpoke formerly, was but in jeſt. One Night, when we were ſpeaking of retiring from Court, I brought him to promiſe, that he ſhould wait on me the next Morning, to give me an ample Declaration of what I ſought of him, but he changed his Mind that very Night, and told me the next day, that he would do it ſome other time, when our Affairs were better ripened. Being aſtoniſh'd at this ſudden change, I found by inquiry, that the Cardinal had ſent for him that very Night, and that he was in his Privy-Chamber above an Hour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and what paſt betwixt them two, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not devine, but by the event. Notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all this,</hi> concludes <hi>Monſieur's</hi> Letter, <hi>I cannot think but this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfortunate has left ſome ſuch Declaration in the hands of ſome of his Friends, which if it could be fallen upon, would mightily conduce to the good of our Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In this Letter, we ſee <hi>Monſieur</hi> aſſerts plainly, that <hi>Monſieur le Grand</hi> confeſſed to him <hi>his Privacies</hi> with the Queen, and had promiſed in his angry Fits, to declare them under his hand, tho' I muſt ſay, it was not generous on his part, let the Queens Ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:110746:16"/> to him be what it will; and it's more than probable, that the taking vent of this Affair, haſtned his Ruine. It ſeems <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demoſelle,</hi> who is yet alive, Daughter to <hi>Monſieur,</hi> was perſwaded of the truth of this <hi>Intrigue,</hi> and that her Father had told her how little Right <hi>Lowis the Fourteenth</hi> had to the Crown, ſince a great many Years after, at <hi>the Barricado of Paris,</hi> this <hi>Princeſs</hi> went in Perſon to the <hi>Baſtile,</hi> and with her own Hand Fir'd <hi>the firſt Gun</hi> againſt the King's Forces, with this Expreſſion, <hi>I know of no Right he has here.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If <hi>likeneſs</hi> be a Sign of a near Relation, never was there two Faces liker to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, than theſe of our <hi>Invincible Monarch,</hi> and <hi>M. le Grand;</hi> and I muſt acknowledge the Wiſdom of the Queen, in cauſing <hi>M. le Viſme,</hi> her Painter, to call in all the Pictures of <hi>M. le Grand</hi> that he could poſſibly get into his Hands, when ſhe found her Son betray'd his true Father by his Phyſiognomy; for thoſe who have ſeen <hi>both the Originals,</hi> will ſay, there was need of all this caution.</p>
            <p>Thus the Cardinal <hi>Richelew</hi> had the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of being a <hi>Gallant</hi> to a Queen, and upon trial of his own want of <hi>a prolifick quality,</hi> had the goodneſs to provide another better qualified than himſelf: Notwithſtanding of this Obligation the Nation has to him, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not forgive <hi>his Inſolence</hi> in ordering theſe Words to be Engraven in <hi>Capital Letters</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:110746:17"/> on the <hi>Pedeſtal</hi> of <hi>Lowis the Thirteenth</hi>'s Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, in <hi>the Palace Royal, Cardinalis Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieus Coadjutor ſuus in omnibus ſuis Negotiis, The Cardinal</hi> Richlew <hi>his Helper in all his Affairs:</hi> As if it had not been enough to have Cuckold'd his Maſter, without erecting him a Statue, meerly to tell the World <hi>that he did ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As <hi>Similitude in Faces</hi> is often a Sign of a <hi>Relation in Blood,</hi> ſo the <hi>Likeneſs of Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> is as often an <hi>Incentive to Love,</hi> and the <hi>Motive to Friendſhip:</hi> Let no Body therefore blame <hi>Lowis the Great,</hi> for Patronizing the <hi>little Prince of Wales;</hi> it's but reaſonable the <hi>Great Baſtard</hi> ſhould protect <hi>the Little One,</hi> and endeavour to ſet upon <hi>the Engliſh Throne</hi> juſt ſuch a Creature as is already upon <hi>the French one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's juſt with our <hi>Great Baſtard,</hi> as with the <hi>Fox</hi> in the Fable, who had the Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune to loſe his Tail; he would needs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade his Neighbours to cut off <hi>theirs,</hi> that thereby he might hide his own Infirmity. It's certain <hi>Lowis the Fourteenth</hi> would be content, that all the Scepters of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> were only ſway'd by <hi>Baſtards,</hi> that his own <hi>Spuriouſneſs</hi> might be the leſs taken notice of. And if it be true, that ſome <hi>Lawyers</hi> affirm of the old Law of <hi>Normandy,</hi> that by it <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtards</hi> did exclude <hi>the lawfully begotten,</hi> no Body has Reaſon to exclaim againſt <hi>Lowis le Grand</hi> his Succeſſion to the Crown of <hi>France,</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:110746:17"/> ſince he is a <hi>Norman</hi> by Birth, as Born at St. <hi>Germain en Laye,</hi> the hithermoſt Town of that Province.</p>
            <p>Methinks I hear <hi>the little Prince of Wales,</hi> or rather his <hi>true Parents,</hi> exclaiming againſt me heavily, for calling him ſo often a <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard,</hi> and thus pleading againſt the Injuſtice of my Pen: <hi>What Devil muſt inſpire a Man to call one a Baſtard that is really begotten in lawful Wedlock! and though he had the good Fortune to be brought into Queen</hi> Marys <hi>Bed by a skilful Midwife, to be there own'd for her own Son, yet all this makes him not a Baſtard: And pray who would have refuſed to lend their Son to be the Heir of three Crowns?</hi> I confeſs there is Reaſon in all this; and I am very inclinable to excuſe both <hi>the little Impoſter</hi> and <hi>his Parents,</hi> ſince few would have refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſuch an Offer; and I oblige my ſelf, That if ever I happen to be in <hi>England</hi> when the Gentleman comes to be King, I ſhall beg his Pardon, for giving him <hi>a Name</hi> he deſerves not.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
